inside your desktop computer
在你的台式电脑里
are more than a dozen different memory
有十几个不同的记忆
and storage locations
和存储位置
where data can be found
在哪里可以找到数据
specifically all your video games
特别是你所有的电子游戏
applications and files
应用程序和文件
are stored in the SSD and hard drive
存储在SSD和硬盘中
however when you load an application or video game
但是，当您加载应用程序或视频游戏时
gigabytes of data are transferred
千兆字节的数据被传输
to the sticks of DRAM
到DRAM的棍子
the VRAM in the graphics card
显卡中的VRAM
and many other memory locations
和许多其他内存位置
throughout the CPU and GPU
整个CPU和GPU
thereby enabling you to smoothly explore massive
从而使您能够顺利地探索大规模
3D worlds and immersive environments
3D世界和沉浸式环境
in contrast
相比之下
if your computer only used a few of these memory
如果您的计算机只使用了其中的一些内存
locations then the game would either take days to load
然后游戏需要几天才能加载
and run at a snail's pace
以蜗牛的速度奔跑
or be limited to the simplest of graphics
或仅限于最简单的图形
the science and engineering behind how data
数据背后的科学和工程
and files are stored
并存储文件
is incredibly complicated
非常复杂
so we've divided this video into three parts
所以我们把这个视频分成三个部分
first we'll build a visual
首先我们要建立一个视觉
to demonstrate the fundamental reason
证明根本原因
why computers need so many different data
为什么计算机需要这么多不同的数据
storage locations
存储位置
second we'll investigate the nanoscopic structures
其次，我们将研究纳米结构
physical designs and limitations of
物理设计和限制
each device and location
每个设备和位置
and see how they work
看看它们是如何工作的
and then third
然后第三个
we'll look into the cutting edge
我们会研究最前沿的
memory and data storage systems used inside AI
AI内部使用的内存和数据存储系统
servers and data centers
服务器和数据中心
essentially we'll explore every aspect of cache
本质上，我们将探索缓存的各个方面
memory
记忆
and storage inside desktop computers and AI servers
以及台式电脑和AI服务器内的存储
and show you how it all works
并向您展示这一切是如何运作的
so let's jump right in
所以让我们开始吧
this video is sponsored by Micron
本视频由美光赞助
a leading producer of advanced memory
高级内存的领先生产商
and storage solutions
和存储解决方案
including DRAM and 3D Nan flash SSD technologies
包括DRAM和3D楠闪存SSD技术
which we'll be featuring
我们将以它为特色
that said all the facts and details presented
上面写着所有的事实和细节
have been independently researched
已独立研究
written and animated
书面和动画
over a dozen different memory and storage locations
超过十几个不同的内存和存储位置
seem like a lot
看起来很多
so why does your computer need them all
那么为什么您的计算机需要它们呢？
well the main idea is that each type of memory
主要的想法是每种类型的记忆
has vastly different
有很大的不同
storage capacity
存储容量
access time bandwidth and cost
接入时间带宽和成本
for example
例如
hard drives and SSDs have a ton of storage capacity
硬盘驱动器和SSD有大量的存储容量
and are cheap
而且很便宜。
but have horrible access times and bandwidth
但访问时间和带宽都很糟糕
in contrast CPU cache
相比之下，CPU缓存
memory
记忆
has lightning fast access times and high bandwidth
具有闪电般的快速访问时间和高带宽
but is expensive and doesn't store much data
但很昂贵并且存储的数据不多
essentially no single memory
基本上没有单一内存
each location has five stars in all these attributes
每个位置在所有这些属性上都有五颗星
however by connecting them all together
然而，通过将它们连接在一起
and using memory controllers
并使用内存控制器
and sophisticated algorithms to move
和复杂的算法来移动
data between locations
位置间数据
your computer can run with a combined 5 stars
您的计算机可以运行组合5星
across the board
一刀切
here are the specs for each of these memory locations
以下是每个内存位置的规格
however
然而
these numbers are rather boring and easily forgotten
这些数字相当无聊，很容易忘记
so instead let's use a visualization
所以让我们使用可视化
to illustrate the massive differences between them
来说明他们之间的巨大差异
we'll start with the first two attributes
我们将从前两个属性开始
which are storage capacity and access time
即存储容量和访问时间
for storage we'll represent 1 megabyte of data
对于存储，我们将表示1兆字节的数据
as a 400 page book
作为一本400页的书
and interestingly with each letter
有趣的是，每封信
punctuation Mark and space equal to an 8 bit
标点符号标记和空格等于8位
ASCII character
ASCII字符
400 pages of text is very close to 1 megabyte
400页的文本非常接近1兆字节
so it's a fitting comparison
所以这是一个合适的比较
next is access time
接下来是访问时间
which is the time between sending a request for data
这是发送数据请求之间的时间
or a specific book
或特定的书
and that book traveling back to the requester
那本书会被送回请求者那里
we'll depict access time by the distance between data
我们将通过数据之间的距离来描述访问时间
storage locations
存储位置
with 20 centimeters equal to 1 nanosecond
20厘米等于1纳秒
with these two attributes in mind
考虑到这两个属性
let's begin with a CPU
让我们从CPU开始
which will represent as a table in a library
它将表示为库中的表
within the CPU
在CPU内
data is stored as open spaces for books
数据存储为书籍的开放空间
and individual pages
和单个页面
inside three levels of cache memory and registers
在三级缓存和寄存器内
the CPU is divided into eight performance cores and 16
CPU分为八个性能核心和16个
efficient cores
有效核心
with the registers L1 and L2 cache
使用寄存器L1和L2缓存
divided between each of the cores
在每个核心之间划分
whereas the L3 cache is shared among all of the cores
而L3缓存在所有内核之间共享
all these memory locations
所有这些内存位置
take up approximately 30 percent of the area
占据了大约百分之三十的面积
of the actual CPU die
实际的CPU芯片
and in total 68 megabytes or books can be stored
总共可以存储68兆字节或书籍
as well as sundry pages for the registers and L1 caches
以及寄存器和L1缓存的各种页面
the remaining
剩余的
70 percent of the CPU is taken up by each core's
70%的CPU被每个内核占用
functional logic
功能逻辑
device and memory controllers and many other sections
设备和内存控制器以及许多其他部分
to clearly depict access time
清楚地描述访问时间
we'll rearrange the CPU
我们会重新安排CPU
with the ALU
用ALU
calculators and execution units on one side
一边是计算器和执行单元
and the registers and caches spread across the table
寄存器和缓存分布在桌子上
as you can see
如你所见
the registers are a third of a nanosecond away
寄存器在三分之一纳秒之外
from the ALU calculators
从ALU计算器
in contrast the shared
相比之下，共享
36 megabytes or books
36兆字节或书籍
and the L3
还有L3
caches are on the other side of the table at
缓存在桌子的另一边
75 nanoseconds away
75纳秒的距离
let's move on to the DRAM
让我们继续DRAM
which will represent the short library carts
这将代表短图书馆推车
next to the table
在桌子旁边
with two sticks of 16 gigabyte DRAM
用两根16 GB的DRAM
all these carts can hold the equivalent of
所有这些手推车能装相当于
32 thousand books
3.20万书
which is 470 times the capacity of the CPU
是CPU容量的470倍
the trade off is that
权衡是
moving data from the CPU to the DRAM
将数据从CPU移动到DRAM
takes around 45 nanoseconds
大约需要45纳秒
so most of the DRAM
所以大部分DRAM
carts are positioned 9 meters away from the CPU table
推车距离CPU工作台9米
next up is the graphics card
接下来是显卡
which contains the GPU and VRAM chips
其中包含GPU和VRAM芯片
the GPU table can hold approximately 37 MB
GPU表可以容纳大约37 MB
across its registers L1 and L2 caches
通过其寄存器L1和L2缓存
which together take up a third of the die
它们一起占据了三分之一的模具
with the rest being functional logic
其余的是功能逻辑
however
然而
because the GPU has 10,000 ish individual cores
因为GPU有10,000个左右的独立内核
the distribution of memory is a little different
内存的分布有点不同
from that on the CPU
从CPU上的那个
next to the GPU table are the VRAM chip library carts
GPU表旁边是VRAM芯片库推车
which hold 24 gigabytes and are
它可以容纳24 GB并且是
250 nanoseconds away from the GPU
距离GPU 250纳秒
this additional distance is due to the VRAM's design
这个额外的距离是由于VRAM的设计
which prioritizes higher bandwidth
优先考虑更高的带宽
using wider buses and deep pipelines
使用更宽的总线和深管道
rather than single request access time
而不是单个请求访问时间
additionally it takes an average of
此外，它需要平均
300 nanoseconds to request and send data
300纳秒请求和发送数据
from the CPU to the GPU
从CPU到GPU
thereby placing the two devices 60 meters apart
从而将两个设备相距60米
with the CPU GPU and both types of main memory covered
涵盖CPU GPU和两种类型的主存储器
let's move on to the storage devices
让我们继续讨论存储设备
which are the two solid state drives
哪两个是固态硬盘
or SSDs and the hard drive
或者SSD和硬盘
the first NVME solid state drive
第一款NVME固态硬盘
holds 2 million books on an array of 2,000 bookshelves
在2000个书架上放着200万本书
with each bookshelf holding a gigabyte of data
每个书架都有千兆字节的数据
the next SATA SSD
下一个SATA SSD
holds 4 million books across 4,000 bookshelves
可容纳4000个书架上的400万本书
and the hard disk drive holds a whopping
硬盘驱动器的容量非常大
8 million books
800万书
although
虽然
these locations store thousands of times more data
这些位置存储了数千倍的数据
when we consider their access time
当我们考虑他们的访问时间时
the NVME and SATA SSDs
NVME和SATA SSD
are positioned at 80 and 120 microseconds away
位于80和120微秒之外
which is analogous to 16 and
这类似于16和
24 kilometers respectively
分别24公里
and then way further out is the hard drive
然后更远的地方是硬盘
with a 10 millisecond access time or
具有10毫秒的访问时间或
2000 kilometers away
2000公里以外
as you can see with this visualization
正如你在这个可视化中看到的
there's a staggeringly large trade off
有一个惊人的巨大的权衡
in the magnitudes of differences in storage capacity
存储容量差异的大小
and access time
和访问时间
among all these locations
在所有这些地点中
one important thing to note
需要注意的一件重要事情
is that in a university level
这是大学水平的吗？
computer architecture course
计算机架构课程
discussions on memory and storage
关于内存和存储的讨论
would typically be organized into a pyramid
通常会被组织成金字塔
called the memory hierarchy
称为内存层次结构
with registers and cash at the top
上面有收银机和现金
DRAM in the middle and SSDs and hard drives below that
DRAM在中间，SSD和硬盘在下面
along with arrows
还有箭
to depict the trends and the various attributes
描绘趋势和各种属性
additionally there's another layer at the bottom
另外底部还有一层
for the internet and other devices
用于互联网和其他设备
so let's incorporate the internet and cloud storage
所以让我们结合互联网和云存储
into our visualization
进入我们的可视化
to start
开始
the internet holds absurdly large amounts of data
互联网拥有荒谬的大量数据
at approximately 500 exabytes
大约500艾字节
latency varies
延迟各不相同
depending on the distance
取决于距离
the request and return data need to travel
请求和返回数据需要旅行
therefore getting data from a nearby city
因此从附近的城市获取数据
takes approximately
大约需要
12 milliseconds
12毫秒
in contrast sending
对比发送
and receiving data to the other side of the earth
并将数据接收到地球的另一边
takes on average a quarter of a second
平均需要四分之一秒
which interestingly
有趣的是
is about twice as long as
大约是
if light were to travel the same distance
如果光传播相同的距离
that is of course
那是当然
as long as you're not using a dial up toaster
只要你不用拨号烤面包机
as a modem
作为调制解调器
let's next
我们接下来
explore and correlate the physical structure
探索和关联物理结构
inside these memory and storage locations
在这些内存和存储位置内
with each of their attributes
他们的每一个属性
we'll start with a 2 terabyte NVME solid state drive
我们将从2TB的NVME固态硬盘开始
mounted to the SSD's circuit board
安装到SSD的电路板上
are a memory controller DRAM
是内存控制器DRAM
and a pair of
和一双
3D NAND flash chip packages
3D NAND闪存芯片封装
where all the files are stored
所有文件的存储位置
so let's open it up
所以让我们打开它
inside we find a stack of eight dies
在里面我们找到了一叠八个模具
with wires connecting each one to a substrate
用电线将每一个连接到基板
at the bottom a single die contains multiple planes
在底部，单个模具包含多个平面
and when we zoom in on one of the planes
当我们放大其中一架飞机时
we see a massive array of memory cells
我们看到大量的记忆细胞
40,000 strings wide
40,000弦宽
60,000 rows deep and stacked around 200 layers tall
60,000排深，大约200层高
in total this array of memory cells can store
总的来说，这个存储单元阵列可以存储
more than 100 gigabytes of data
超过100 GB的数据
in a volume smaller than a grain of rice
体积小于一粒米
while costing only 7 cents per gigabyte
而每GB仅需7美分
but how does it physically store data
但是它如何物理存储数据呢？
well let's zoom in to see a single memory cell called
好吧，让我们放大看看一个名为
charge trap flash or CTF
电荷陷阱闪存或CTF
which stores data
存储数据
by trapping eight distinct amounts of charge
通过捕获八个不同数量的电荷
or electrons corresponding to three bits of data
或对应于三位数据的电子
the electrons are held in a charge trap
电子被保持在电荷阱中
surrounded by an insulating dielectric
被绝缘电介质包围
enabling data to be stored for years
使数据能够存储数年
without external power
无外力
the trade off is that
权衡是
due to the lack of a direct electrical connection
由于缺乏直接的电气连接
writing or moving electrons into the charge trap
将电子写入或移动到电荷阱中
and reading or measuring the stored charge
并读取或测量存储的电荷
requires applying a complex sequence of voltage steps
需要施加一系列复杂的电压步骤
that take dozens of microseconds to complete
需要几十微秒才能完成
resulting in a read time of around 80 microseconds
导致读取时间约为80微秒
a write time closer to 500 microseconds
接近500微秒的写入时间
and 5 gigabytes per second of bandwidth
和每秒5 GB的带宽
it's important to note that
重要的是要注意
even if a CPU core were placed
即使放置了CPU内核
directly next to the array of CTF
直接在CTF阵列旁边
memory cells the access time would still be close to
访问时间仍将接近
80 microseconds
80微秒
therefore
因此
it's important to clarify that in our visualization
在我们的可视化中澄清这一点很重要
the distance between objects
物体之间的距离
isn't the time it takes electricity to travel
不是需要电力才能旅行的时间吗？
but rather access time
而是访问时间
is determined by the limitations of the storage medium
是由存储介质的限制决定的
itself and in a way
本身和在某种程度上
you can think of it
你能想到的
like the time and effort required in reaching books
就像看书所需的时间和精力一样
on a very tall bookshelf
在一个非常高的书架上
another note is that SATA
另一个注意事项是SATA
SSDs use a similar set of chips
SSD使用一组类似的芯片
including the same 3D NAND flash
包括相同的3D NAND闪光灯
resulting in comparable costs
导致可比成本
however they have longer access times
但是他们有更长的访问时间
and substantially lower bandwidth
和显着降低的带宽
due to limitations in the older SATA
由于旧SATA的限制
data transfer protocol
数据搬迁协议
so take that into consideration
所以考虑到这一点
when you build or buy your next computer
当您构建或购买下一台计算机时
let's move on and explore the hard disk drive
让我们继续探索硬盘驱动器
inside it we find a stack of four platters with eight
在里面，我们发现了一叠四个盘子和八个
read right heads controlled by a voice coil motor
读右头由音圈电机控制
data is stored across the platter
数据存储在整个盘片中
in half a million concentric circles
在50万个同心圆中
called tracks
称为轨道
zooming in we see individual sectors
放大我们看到单个扇区
each with a preamble or synchronization zone
每个都有一个前导或同步区
an address 4 kilobytes of data
一个地址4 KB的数据
an error correcting code and gaps between sectors
纠错码和扇区之间的间隙
when we zoom into a nanoscopic view
当我们放大纳米视图时
we see that data is written using focused
我们看到数据是使用聚焦写入的
magnetic fields to manipulate the magnetic domains
磁场来操纵磁畴
inside a nanometer sized volume within the platter
在盘子内的纳米大小的体积内
at the same time
同时
the readhead senses a change in magnetic fields
读数头感应到磁场的变化
between domains
域间
as one and no change as zero
为一，不变为零
as a result
结果
trillions of bits can fit across the platters area
数万亿比特可以穿过盘片区域
yielding terabytes of storage in a single hard drive
在单个硬盘驱动器中产生TB的存储空间
hard drives cost only ￠1 or 2 per gigabyte
硬盘成本仅为每GB 1或2美分
because the platters are simply layers of material
因为拼盘只是一层层的材料
on a disk rather than complex semiconductor structures
而不是复杂的半导体结构
however
然而
there are considerable costs in the Reed right heads
Reed家的右脑要付出相当大的代价
which must be engineered to fly only
它必须设计成只能飞行
nanometers above the spinning surface
在旋转表面上方纳米
the main trade off of hard drives
硬盘驱动器的主要权衡
is that they have long access times and low bandwidth
它们的访问时间长，带宽低
because the read write head must physically move to
因为读写头必须物理移动到
or seek the correct location on the platter
或者寻找拼盘上的正确位置
while it spins around at 7200 RPM
当它以每1k7200展现的收入
while this may seem incredibly fast
虽然这看起来快得难以置信
it equates to one rotation every
它等于每旋转一次
83 milliseconds yielding an access time in that range
83毫秒产生该范围内的访问时间
with storage covered let's discuss main memory
有了存储，让我们讨论主存储器
in these sticks of DRAM
在这些DRAM棒中
each one contains
每一个都包含
eight chips that directly connect to the CPU
八个直接连接CPU的芯片
via the motherboard's memory channels
通过主板的内存通道
and are all managed by the CPU's memory controller
并且都由CPU的内存控制器管理
upon opening one of these DRAM chips
打开这些DRAM芯片之一时
we find a set of interconnected
我们找到一组相互关联的
layers and an integrated circuit containing 32 banks
层和包含32组的集成电路
with each one
每一个
consisting of an array of approximately 65,000
由大约65,000个阵列组成
by 8,000 memory cells
8,000个记忆单元
when we zoom in
当我们放大时
we can see individual memory cells
我们可以看到单个的记忆细胞
built from one transistor and one capacitor
由一个晶体管和一个电容器组成
hence the name 1t 1c
因此得名1t 1c
one bit is stored as charge in each capacitor
一个位作为电荷存储在每个电容器中
and the transistor is used to access that data
晶体管用于访问该数据
to read or write data
读取或写入数据
the CPU sends an address for a specific bank and row
CPU发送特定银行和行的地址
thereby turning on all the transistors in that row
从而打开该行中的所有晶体管
and directly connecting each capacitor to a
并将每个电容器直接连接到
sense amplifier
读出放大器
the sense amplifiers measure the voltage
读出放大器测量电压
in each capacitor
在每个电容器中
and then a set of eight sense amplifiers
然后是一组八个读出放大器
is connected to either the read or write drivers
连接到读取或写入驱动程序
which relay data to and from the CPU
它将数据中继到CPU和从CPU中继数据
in total taking around 45 nanoseconds
总共需要大约45纳秒
additionally DRAM has a much higher bandwidth
此外，DRAM具有更高的带宽
typically around 48 gigabytes per second
通常大约每秒48 GB
which allows the operating system to quickly context
它允许操作系统快速上下文
switch between processes
进程间切换
the trade off is that
权衡是
due to the physical size of the capacitor
由于电容器的物理尺寸
the 1t 1C array is typically confined to a 2d plane
1t 1C阵列通常仅限于二维平面
resulting in a lower bit density
导致较低的位密度
and higher cost per bit
和更高的每比特成本
additionally each capacitor quickly loses its charge
此外，每个电容器很快就会失去电荷
therefore
因此
every memory cell must be frequently refreshed
每个存储单元都必须经常刷新
and without power
而且没有权力
DRAM would lose all its data in a tenth of a second
DRAM会在十分之一秒内丢失所有数据
finally let's move on to the structure of cache memory
最后让我们继续讨论缓存的结构
and registers inside the CPU
并在CPU内注册
they're both made of transistors
它们都是用晶体管做的
resulting in incredibly fast access times
导致令人难以置信的快速访问时间
and high bandwidth
和高带宽
cache memory uses six transistors per bit
高速缓冲存储器每比特使用六个晶体管
assembled into an SRAM cell
组装成SRAM单元
while six transistors may seem small
虽然六个晶体管看起来很小
when we multiply this by
当我们把这个乘以
36 megabytes in the L3 cache
L3缓存中的36兆字节
we get
我们得到
18 billion transistors
180亿晶体管
adding in the other two levels of caches
添加其他两个级别的缓存
along with the space for each address
以及每个地址的空间
results in approximately a third of the CPU's
导致大约三分之一的CPU
26 billion transistors being dedicated to cash
260亿晶体管专用于现金
factoring in the cost of a CPU
考虑CPU的成本
and extrapolating the cash to a gigabyte of storage
并将现金推断为千兆字节的存储空间
yields absurdly high prices and transistor counts
产生荒谬的高价格和晶体管数量
which is why the capacity of cash is so small
这就是为什么现金容量如此之小
as for registers
至于寄存器
they store bits in d flip flops
他们将比特存储在d触发器中
using around 16 transistors per bit
每比特使用大约16个晶体管
each register is typically 64 bits wide
每个寄存器通常为64位宽
and each processing core contains
每个处理核心都包含
32 registers or entries in a register file
寄存器文件中的32个寄存器或条目
there are two reasons why
有两个原因
register files are rather small
寄存器文件相当小
first registers are designed to be accessed
第一个寄存器旨在访问
in a single clock cycle
在一个时钟周期内
or 1/3 of an nanosecond
或者1/3纳秒
and increasing the number of entries
并增加参赛人数
would require larger decoder circuitry
需要更大的解码器电路
and more ports needed to access all the registers
以及访问所有寄存器所需的更多端口
this additional circuitry
这个附加电路
would require a slower clock speed
需要较慢的时钟速度
thereby slowing down your computer
从而减慢您的计算机速度
second 32
第二个32
registers are addressed using five bits
寄存器使用五位寻址
within the instructions themselves
在说明本身内
and therefore
因此
increasing the number of registers
增加寄存器数量
would require longer instructions
需要更长的说明
in essence
本质上
registers sit directly next to the execution units
寄存器直接位于执行单元旁边
and the arithmetic logic unit
和算术逻辑单元
where the cores calculations
核心计算的地方
and logic operations occur
并发生逻辑运算
and then
然后
spread across the table are the different cache
分布在表中的是不同的缓存
levels and sizes
级别和大小
this visualization is useful
这种可视化很有用
because execution units can only work on data
因为执行单元只能处理数据
that's already in the registers
已经登记在案了
so if the data is not there
所以如果数据不在那里
it must be fetched from the cache hierarchy
它必须从缓存层次结构中获取
main memory
主存储器
or even storage and gradually moved into the registers
甚至存储并逐渐进入寄存器
having covered the physical design of registers caches
涵盖了寄存器缓存的物理设计
DRAM hard disk drives and solid state drives
DRAM硬盘驱动器和固态驱动器
it's important to note that
重要的是要注意
the sizes and access times we used are approximate
我们使用的尺寸和访问时间是近似的
because manufacturers rarely publish
因为制造商很少发布
all of their internal specs
他们所有的内部规格
for example our SSD model
例如我们的SSD型号
with roughly 40 by 60,000 by 200 CTF cells per plane
每架飞机大约有40 x 60,000 x 200个CTF细胞
and two planes per die
每个模具两架飞机
is intended to be in the realistic ballpark
目的是在现实的棒球场
rather than an exact blueprint
而不是确切的蓝图
in practice there are hundreds of different designs
实际上有数百种不同的设计
and architectures
和架构
for each type of storage
对于每种类型的存储
and technology is continually improving
技术在不断进步
so in a decade
所以十年后
these devices will likely be many times larger
这些设备可能会大很多倍
and offer much faster access times
并提供更快的访问时间
and higher bandwidth
和更高的带宽
furthermore
更进一步
there are also other memory technologies such as
还有其他内存技术，例如
magnetic RAM and phase change memory
磁性RAM和相变存储器
plus
加
many emerging variants for each level of the hierarchy
层次结构的每个级别都有许多新兴变体
but covering those would take an entire separate
但是覆盖这些需要一个单独的
hour long video
一小时长的视频
so for now let's move on
所以现在让我们继续前进
the final topic we'll explore
我们将探讨的最后一个主题
is the cutting edge memory and storage systems
是最前沿的内存和存储系统
used inside AI servers and data centers
在AI服务器和数据中心内使用
AI runs on incredibly advanced AI accelerators
人工智能运行在非常先进的人工智能加速器上
and AI processors
和人工智能处理器
that execute pedophops of calculations
执行恋童癖的计算
and require two orders of magnitude
并且需要两个数量级
more memory and storage than a typical desktop computer
比典型的台式计算机更多的内存和存储空间
specifically inside a single AI server
特别是在单个AI服务器内
there can be terabytes of memory
可以有TB的内存
and hundreds of terabytes of storage
和数百TB的存储空间
however this raises the question
然而，这提出了一个问题
if a paragraph's text
如果一段文字
when converted to binary using ASCII
使用ASCII转换为二进制时
occupies only a few hundred bytes
只占用几百个字节
why does AI
为什么人工智能
need such large amounts of memory and storage
需要如此大量的内存和存储空间
well essentially
基本上
AI needs to build an understanding of the input text
人工智能需要建立对输入文本的理解
and it does this by using roughly between 2 and 8
它大约使用2到8之间来做到这一点
thousand dimensions or values per word
每个单词的千个维度或值
each one byte in size
每个字节的大小
technically an AI uses tokens
从技术上讲，人工智能使用代币
which can sometimes be a part of a word
有时是单词的一部分
but for simplicity we'll say one word equals one token
但是为了简单起见，我们说一个词等于一个标记。
and that each token uses 8,000 dimensions
每个代币使用8,000个维度
we're planning
我们正在计划
many more videos that will dive deeper into AI
更多视频将更深入地了解人工智能
but for now we'll provide a high level explanation
但现在我们会提供一个高层次的解释
so then what are these 8,000 dimensions or values
那么这8000个维度或值是什么？
well a simplified way of thinking about it
嗯，一种简化的思考方式
is that the word dog for example
例如，这是狗这个词吗？
is Learned and understood by the AI
被人工智能学习和理解
by assigning different values
通过分配不同的值
for a subset of the 8,000 dimensions
对于8,000个维度的子集
relating to certain attributes
与某些属性有关
in order to embed
为了嵌入
or establish an understanding of that word
或者建立对这个词的理解
for example some dimensions are used to represent
例如，一些维度用于表示
attributes of the word
词的属性
such as temperature and how hot or cold the word is
比如温度和这个词有多热或多冷
or size and how big or small the word or token is
或大小以及单词或标记的大小
as a result each token has 8000 dimensions or values
因此，每个令牌都有8000个维度或值
each one byte in size resulting in 8 kilobytes of data
每个字节的大小导致8 KB的数据
however the AI needs to work with paragraphs of text
然而，人工智能需要处理文本段落
which yields much more data
这产生了更多的数据
specifically
具体地说
the maximum number of tokens in AI can handle
AI中可以处理的最大代币数量
is called a context window
称为上下文窗口
and for cutting edge models
对于尖端型号
is around 100,000 to a couple of million tokens
大约是10万到几百万个代币
the context window includes not only the input text
上下文窗口不仅包括输入文本
but also prior conversations the answer or output text
但之前的对话也是答案或输出文本
other reference text and much more
其他参考文本等等
therefore a context window of 1 million tokens
因此100万标记的上下文窗口
each with 8,000 dimensions
每个都有8000个维度
results in 8 gigabytes of data
产生8 GB的数据
to generate a response
生成响应
the AI must feed the million token context window
AI必须提供百万令牌上下文窗口
through hundreds of transformer blocks
通过数百个变压器块
these blocks include attention sublayers
这些块包括注意力子层
feed forward or multi layer perceptron blocks
前馈或多层感知器块
variations of mixture of experts blocks
混合专家块的变体
and many other components
和许多其他组件
each block is made from tens of millions of learn
每个区块都是由数千万个学习组成的
parameters and therefore
参数，因此
state of the art AI models
最先进的人工智能模型
are built from hundreds of billions of parameters
是由数千亿个参数构建的
while the context window passes through
当上下文窗口通过时
each of these blocks
这些块中的每一个
and billions of parameters of the AI model
以及AI模型的数十亿参数
all these numbers must be stored in memory
所有这些数字都必须存储在内存中
and continuously fed to and from the AI processors
并不断输入和输出AI处理器
resulting in tremendous amounts of data movement
导致大量数据移动
and the need for AI to have enormous amounts of memory
以及人工智能需要拥有大量内存
as a result
结果
AI also uses a memory hierarchy but dialed up to 11
AI也使用内存层次结构，但最多拨打11
and that's where this video's sponsor Micron operates
这就是该视频的赞助商美光运营的地方
Micron has pioneered a new memory hierarchy for AI
美光开创了人工智能的新内存层次结构
processors that divides memory into near memory
将内存划分为近内存的处理器
called high Bandwidth Memory or HBM
称为高带宽存储器或HBM
this tier uses HBM 3e and HBM 4
此层使用HBM 3e和HBM 4
located next to the AI chip itself
位于AI芯片本身旁边
the AI memory hierarchy also includes DDR5 server RDIM
AI内存层次结构还包括DDR5服务器RDIM
sticks as main memory
记忆棒作为主存储器
and even more expansion memory using CXL
甚至更多使用CXL的扩展内存
or compute Expresslink protocol
或计算Expresslink协议
to further increase server memory capacity
进一步增加服务器内存容量
this is all before we even touch the storage layers
这都是在我们接触存储层之前
so let's explore each of these layers
所以让我们探索每一层
closest to each AI processor is the HBM 3e
离每个AI处理器最近的是HBM 3e
built from a 12
由12建造
high stack of DRAM dies
高堆叠DRAM模具
that use through silicon vias or TSVs to
通过硅通孔或TSV
connect all the layers
连接所有层
thereby building a compact
从而建立一个契约
memory dense cube into a single package
内存密集立方体成一个包
six of these packages are mounted to an interposer
其中六个包安装在一个内插器上
which is a thin silicon substrate
它是一种薄硅衬底
that sits under the HBM stacks
位于HBM书库下方
in AI processor
在AI处理器中
this interposer acts like a mini motherboard or bridge
这个中介就像一个迷你主板或桥接器
providing ultra dense wiring between the AI
在AI之间提供超密集的布线
processor in the center
中心处理器
and the surrounding 141 gigabytes of HBM
以及周围141 GB的HBM
short yet incredibly wide
短而宽
routes between the AI processor and HPM
AI处理器和HPM之间的路由
deliver an impressive
发表令人印象深刻的
12 terabytes per second of bandwidth
每秒12 TB的带宽
with very low latency
延迟非常低
the next layer down in the AI memory hierarchy
AI内存层次结构中的下一层
is the DDR5 RDIM
是DDR5 RDIM
and 32 sticks each containing 128 gigabytes
和32根每根包含128 GB的棍子
resulting in 4 terabytes of memory
产生4 TB的内存
notably some AI systems use LP DDR
值得注意的是，一些AI系统使用LP DDR
similar to the memory in your phone
类似于手机中的内存
thereby enabling higher bandwidth
从而实现更高的带宽
while delivering low power and efficient performance
同时提供低功耗和高效性能
in addition to memory
除了内存
Micron has pioneered an even more impressive
美光开创了一个更令人印象深刻的
hierarchy for storage
存储层次结构
and pushed the science and engineering inside
并将科学和工程推入其中
SSDs and flash storage
SSD和闪存
in order to fit more data into a single package
为了将更多数据放入一个包中
specifically
具体地说
within the AI chassis are Micron's 9650 series SSDs
AI机箱内是美光的9650系列SSD
each with 8 to 30 terabytes of storage
每个都有8到30 TB的存储空间
which take advantage of the cutting edge Pcie
利用尖端Pcie
Gen 6 protocol
第6代协议
and are engineered to support the extreme throughput
并且旨在支持极端的吞吐量
demands of training
培训需求
and inference pipelines
和推理管道
furthermore
更进一步
in a separate rack are networked data lakes
在一个单独的机架中是联网的数据湖
using Micron's 6600 ion NVME Ssds
使用美光的6600 ion NVME Ssds
with each module shown
每个模块都显示
containing up to 122 terabytes of storage
包含高达122 TB的存储空间
with other form factors reaching as much as
其他外形尺寸高达
246 terabytes
246 TB
as a result a full rack can store dozens
因此，一个完整的机架可以存储几十个
to hundreds of petabytes of data
数百PB的数据
depending on the chassis and SSD density
取决于机箱和SSD密度
making it perfect for storing training data sets
非常适合存储训练数据集
with billions of examples
有数十亿个例子
AI is the most data
人工智能是最多的数据
intensive workload in modern computing
现代计算中的密集工作负载
which is why data center architecture must tightly
这就是为什么数据中心架构必须紧密
integrate multiple layers of memory and storage
集成多层内存和存储
as systems grow more complex and sophisticated
随着系统变得越来越复杂和精密
their memory and storage
他们的记忆和存储
solutions need to become increasingly diverse
解决方案需要变得越来越多样化
and specialized
专业
if you're curious about Micron's AI memory hierarchy
如果您对美光的AI内存层次结构感到好奇
high bandwidth memory or any of Micron's products
高带宽存储器或美光的任何产品
take a look at one of these links in the description
看看描述中的这些链接之一
alternatively
可选择地
if pioneering
如果开拓
the next generation of memory and storage chips
下一代内存和存储芯片
interests you
使你感兴趣
Micron is always looking for talented scientists
美光一直在寻找有才华的科学家
and engineers
和工程师
to help innovate on cutting edge chips
帮助创新尖端芯片
you can find out more about working for Micron using
您可以使用以下方法了解更多关于为美光工作的信息
this link
此链接
this video is only a glimpse of all the science
这段视频只是所有科学的一瞥
engineering
工程学
and technical details involved in modern memory
以及现代记忆所涉及的技术细节
hierarchies and there's a ton of research development
等级制度，有大量的研究发展
and plenty of careers
和大量的职业
focused entirely on the exciting world of data
完全专注于令人兴奋的数据世界
we're thankful to all our Patreon
我们感谢我们所有的赞助人
and YouTube membership
和YouTube会员
sponsors for supporting our videos
支持我们视频的赞助商
if you want to financially support our work
如果你想资助我们的工作
you can find the links in the description below
您可以在下面的描述中找到链接
this is Branch Education
这是分支教育
and we create
我们创造
3d animations that dive deeply into the technology
深入研究这项技术的3d动画
that drives our modern world
驱动着我们的现代世界
watch another branch video
观看另一个分支视频
by clicking one of these cards
通过点击其中一张卡片
or click here to subscribe
或点击这里订阅
thanks for watching to the end
感谢收看到最后